<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"
  xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:itunes="http://www.itunes.com/dtds/podcast-1.0.dtd"
  xmlns:trackback="http://madskills.com/public/xml/rss/module/trackback/">
  <channel>
    <title>Konstantin's Box</title>
    <link>http://konstantinfarrell.github.io</link>
    <description>Konstantin is a full-stack web developer from Portland, Oregon. In his spare time he can be found tinkering away at some code or circuits, making music on whatever instrument he can find, or hacking away at about 4 projects at once. He also occasionally has a decent game of DotA.
</description>
    <pubDate>Sat, 16 Jul 2016 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
    <item>
      <title>Good things to know about CentOS 7</title>
      <link>http://konstantinfarrell.github.io/2016/07/centos</link>
      <description><![CDATA[

]]></description>
      <pubDate>Sat, 16 Jul 2016 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>http://konstantinfarrell.github.io/2016/07/centos</guid>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[![CentOS 7 banner](/files/img/centos7.png)

# There Was a Change

Things aren't quite how they used to be. And that is very annoying for some. At least,
it was for me when I went to do the thing and found out that the thing didn't quite
work as I had originally expected it to. Naturally, I did what any sensible developer in
my situation would do: Immediately began complaining to my coworkers about it.

As usual, this failed to produce anything other than annoyed grunts from my ever-patient
colleagues. So I decided to actually attempt to fix the problem.

Thus, this disorganized and incomplete list of changes in CentOS 7 was born.

For both my benefit and yours. But not Sean's. He knows what he did.

## Wheres My Service

First thing that I noticed was the service commands changing. Back in CentOS 6, commands
like `service httpd restart` or `service postgres restart` would work just fine.
Now the same commands throw a warning. This is because CentOS is pushing to change from
`init` to `systemd`. There are many reasons for this. A great explanation can be found
[here](http://www.tecmint.com/systemd-replaces-init-in-linux/).

The commands that are taking all the jobs are controlled by `systemctl` now.

So

    service httpd restart

Would change to

    systemctl restart httpd

This effects services like `httpd`, `mysql`, `postgresql`, `redis` and more.
A comprehensive tutorial of `systemd` commands can be found
[here](https://www.digitalocean.com/community/tutorials/how-to-use-systemctl-to-manage-systemd-services-and-units)

## IPTables Have Turned

`iptables` has been replaced with `firewalld`.

This is a real pain to find out if you're in a hurry trying to get a project running.
Back in the day you could do

    iptables -I INPUT -p tcp --destination-port 80 -j ACCEPT
    /sbin/service iptables save

and it would set you up for a local project. That's not the case anymore. The equivalent in
`firewalld` is as follows

    firewall-cmd --zone=public --add-port=http/tcp
    firewall-cmd --zone=public --add-port=http/tcp --permanent

Just a little bit more readable.

### I'll Back With Snacks and More Info Later
]]></content:encoded>
      <dc:date>2016-07-16T00:00:00-07:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Docker On Windows Real Quick</title>
      <link>http://konstantinfarrell.github.io/2016/06/docker</link>
      <description><![CDATA[

]]></description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jun 2016 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>http://konstantinfarrell.github.io/2016/06/docker</guid>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[![Docker Banner](/files/img/docker-facebook.png)

You've got a Windows computer. You want to know what the deal with Docker is.

You don't wanna read a whole lot.

Here's how you start.

## Step 1: Download

Download Docker Toolbox from the following link.

[https://www.docker.com/products/docker-toolbox](https://www.docker.com/products/docker-toolbox)

![Docker main page](/files/img/docker-image-1.png)

## Step 2: Install

Double click the executable and leave all the default options checked.

This will install Docker, the Docker Quickstart Terminal, Kitematic and
a variety of other tools Docker uses.

![Docker Installer Dialog](/files/img/docker-image-2.png)

## Step 3: Run Quickstart Terminal

After the install, run the quickstart terminal.
If you see an ASCII whale, you're in the clear.

Make a note the IP address it provides. It is important.

![Docker Shell](/files/img/docker-screenshot.png)

## Step 4: Run Kitematic & Select a Container

Run Kitematic. From here you can add & run any container environment with ease.

As an example I will add a new CentOS box. All I need to do is search for "Centos", and click the
"Create" button on the repository I have chosen.

This will download and install the image, and add a new entry to my list of containers.

![Kitematic Search](/files/img/docker-kitematic-centos.png)

## Step 5: Run The Container & Connect to Docker

The container should have started automatically after installation. If it didn't, you can select
it and press the "Start" button in Kitematic, or you can wait until after you have connected to the VM.

To proceed, you can use either an SSH client like PuTTY, or just use the Docker Quickstart Terminal.

##### If you'd just like to use the Quickstart Terminal, proceed to Step 6.

If you'd like to use SSH, once the machine is set up and running, SSH into the Docker VM with
the IP address provided earlier, using PuTTY or another SSH client.

    DEFAULT LOGIN CREDENTIALS

    Username: docker
    Password: tcuser

![PuTTY Connect](/files/img/docker-putty.png)

## Step 6: Attach Your Session

You're currently in the Boot2Docker VM. You can choose and attach your session to any
of your containers from here.

Here are some useful commands to know

    docker ps               // Shows all running containers
    docker start <name>     // Starts the container named <name>
    docker attach <name>    // Attaches your session to the container <name>

Type `docker attach centos` to attach the session to the container.

Your session should look something like this.

![Docker Attach](/files/img/docker-attach.png)

### And That's Literally It.

You are connected to your environment.

That took all of what? 5 minutes?

Here's a [link](https://docs.docker.com/engine/reference/commandline/) to the
Docker Command Line API if you'd like a comprehensive list of commands.
]]></content:encoded>
      <dc:date>2016-06-23T00:00:00-07:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An Exercize in JavaScript Animations</title>
      <link>http://konstantinfarrell.github.io/2016/05/gribble</link>
      <description><![CDATA[

]]></description>
      <pubDate>Sat, 21 May 2016 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>http://konstantinfarrell.github.io/2016/05/gribble</guid>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<iframe src='/gribble/'></iframe>

# How About That Eh?

Pretty neat, huh? Now try clicking on it. Totally pointless right? Nah it's kinda nice to look at.

Looks like something you wanna make? Ok lets make it.

[Here's a fiddle](https://jsfiddle.net/28p6ox9b/) if you'd like to follow along.

## Step 1: Setup the Environment

Lets start this off in a new `.js` file, with a standard `$(document).ready();` call.

In one of my previous posts, I defined two functions: `toCSS()` and `rcv()`. We're going to reuse that code.

    // Take RGB values and return a CSS formatted string representation.
    function toCSS(r,g,b){
        return "rgb("+r+","+g+","+b+")";
    }

    // Return a pseudorandom number between 0 and 255
    function rcv(){
        return Math.floor(Math.random()*256);
    }

From inside the `$(document).ready();` call, set the background to something with a nice dark color that isn't too sharp. `#111` works fine in this case.
Make the body the fill the viewport, and make sure all overflow data is hidden.

We're going to want to make sure to set a size for our tiles, and give them a delay before shunting them out of the screen.
`30` pixels is what I used as the default size. I also defined a delay of 3 seconds.

Right now your code should look something like this:

    var size = 30;

    // Take RGB values and return a CSS formatted string representation.
    function toCSS(r,g,b){
        return "rgb("+r+","+g+","+b+")";
    }

    // Return a pseudorandom number between 0 and 255
    function rcv(){
        return Math.floor(Math.random()*256);
    }

    $(document).ready(function(e){
        // Style up the body.
        $('body').css({
            'width': '100%',
            'height': '100%',
            'background-color': '#111',
            'overflow': 'hidden',
            'position': 'absolute'
        });
    }):

## Step 2: Place A Tile

It would be nice to have a function with which we could define a tile based on its coordinates, and get some information back for future reference.
This function should take the coordinates as arguments and place the tile respectively. However, we'd like to maintain a grid-like structure for
tile placement.

To do this, we can take the x,y coordinates and create a placement index based on the floor of the coordinate divided by the size
of the tile. That is, we divide the coordinate by the size, and round down.
Since this gives us a unique way to identify each tile, it can be used as part of the tile id.
Before placing the tile, we should check to make sure one with that identifier doesn't already exist.

    var index_X = Math.floor(x/size);
    var index_Y = Math.floor(y/size);
    var name = index_X + "_" + index_Y + "_tile";
    var exists = document.getElementById(name);
    if(exists == null){
        $("body").append("<div id='"+name+"'></div>");
    }

Great! This works, except that the tile just appears in its space. It would look nicer if there was some sort of transition animation.
Inside the `if()` statement, add the following lines.

    $("#"+name).css({'display': 'none'});
    $("#"+name).fadeIn(250).promise();

This will add the element, but won't immediately show it on the page. It will then take 1/4 of a second to fade in.

At this point, a color can be generated, and all we have to do is modify the css to pretty up the tile.

    var color = toCSS(rcv(), rcv(), rcv());
    $("#"+name).css({
        'position': 'absolute',
        'background-color': color,
        'box-shadow': '0 0 1px '+color,
        'border-radius': '2px',
        'top': index_Y * size,
        'left': index_X * size,
        'width': size-3,
        'height': size-3
    });

Now we can return the name as the identifier. Just like that, the tile has been placed.

#### Here is the full code for the function.

    function gribset(x,y){
        var index_X = Math.floor(x/size);
        var index_Y = Math.floor(y/size);
        var name = index_X + "_" + index_Y + "_cell";
        var exists = document.getElementById(name);
        if(exists == null){
            $("body").append("<div id='"+name+"'></div>");
            $("#"+name).css({'display': 'none'});
            $("#"+name).fadeIn(250).promise();
        }

        var color = toCSS(rcv(), rcv(), rcv());
        $("#"+name).css({
            'position': 'absolute',
            'background-color': color,
            'box-shadow': '0 0 1px '+color,
            'border-radius': '2px',
            'top': index_Y * size,
            'left': index_X * size,
            'width': size-3,
            'height': size-3
        });
        return name;
    }

## Step 3: Pick a Direction

We're gonna need one more helper function to determine the direction that each tile should travel.
Since this is essentially a random process, we can simply pick a random number from 0-3, and use a
series of if statements to determine the information that will be returned.

The function should return the direction of travel (vertical or horizontal aka top or left), and the coordinate point
the tile will travel to. Something off the edge of the screen to give the illusion the tile has disappeared.

    function goDirection(){
        var num = Math.floor(Math.random()*4);
        if(num==0){
            return ['top', $(document).height()];
        } else if(num==1){
            return ['left', $(document).width()];
        } else if(num==2){
            return ['top', -100];
        } else if(num==3){
            return ['left', -100];
        }
    }

## Step 4: Shunt!

Great! Now we're ready to make the tiles move! This is the fun part.

Lets use the function we defined above to get a direction and coordinate point.
Lets also randomize the speed at which the tiles move by defining a time interval. Something between
300ms and 900ms.

Once we've got that, we can call the animation.

Here is the code.

    function shunt(name){
        var d = goDirection();
        var direction = d[0];
        var magnitude = d[1];
        var animation = {};
        var time = Math.floor(Math.random() * 600 + 300);
        animation[direction] = magnitude;
        $("#"+name).animate(animation,time).promise().done(function(){
            $("#"+name).remove();
        });
    }

Notice the last line of the function. It calls the animation, then `.promise()` and `.done()`.
This ensures that the following code will not be executed until the current code has finished
processing.

## Step 5: Put it All Together

Now that we've written all the helper functions we're going to need, it's time to write the function
that puts them all together.

This function should be able to create a tile, place it, shunt it, then remove it.
It should take the coordinate points as arguments, and feed them to the `gribset` function.

This will place a tile on the page, set its color, and animate its appearance.
Then after a brief pause, the function should either make the tile fade out, or shunt if off the page.

Since we're in the business of randomizing values, we'll do that with the pause time-interval value as well.

Here's how my function looks.

    function gribble(x,y){
        var name = gribset(x,y);
        var memory = Math.floor(Math.random()*2000+2000)
        setTimeout(function(){
            if(Math.floor(Math.random()*100)%10==0){
                $("#"+name).fadeOut(250).promise().done(function(){
                    $("#"+name).remove();
                });
            } else {
                shunt(name);
            }
        }, memory);
    }

As you can see, there is a 1/10 chance of the tile disappearing after a time interval between 2 and 4 seconds.
If it doesn't disappear, it gets shunted off the screen.

## Step 6: Bring it to Life

We've done all the heavy lifting at this point. In order to get the effect seen in the frame at the top of the page,
the function should be called after random time intervals, with random coordinates.

    function demo_gribble(){
        var x = Math.floor(Math.random()* $(document).width());
        var y = Math.floor(Math.random()* $(document).height());
        var time = Math.floor(Math.random() * 450 + 50);
        gribble(x,y);
        setTimeout(function(){
            demo_gribble();
        }, time);
    }

All that's left is to add a call to this in the `$(document).ready();` function.
Like so.

    $(document).ready(function(e){
        $('body').css({
            'width': '100%',
            'height': '100%',
            'background-color': '#111',
            'overflow': 'hidden',
            'position': 'absolute'
        });

        demo_gribble();
    })

## Step 7: Click Behavior (Optional)

This part is optional, but it would be nice if the user was able to click on the page to generate a tile at that location.
All you have to do is add this to the `$(document).ready()` function.

    $(document).click(function(e){
        var x = e.clientX;
        var y = e.clientY;
        gribble(x, y);
    });

And it's all done. That's all you need.

## Here Is The Full Code

Along with a [link](/gribble/) to the full-page version


    var size = 30;

    // Take RGB values and return a CSS formatted string representation.
    function toCSS(r,g,b){
        return "rgb("+r+","+g+","+b+")";
    }

    // Return a pseudorandom number between 0 and 255
    function rcv(){
        return Math.floor(Math.random()*256);
    }

    // Picks a random number from 0 to 3.
    // Based on that number, returns a direction
    // and the closest point at which the tile would
    // be off the screen.
    function goDirection(){
        var num = Math.floor(Math.random()*4);
        if(num==0){
            return ['top', $(document).height()];
        } else if(num==1){
            return ['left', $(document).width()];
        } else if(num==2){
            return ['top', -100];
        } else if(num==3){
            return ['left', -100];
        }
    }

    function gribble(x,y){
        var memory = Math.floor(Math.random()*2000+2000)
        // Create a gribble-tile, and shunt it.
        var name = gribset(x,y);
        // Now pause for a bit before
        setTimeout(function(){
            if(Math.floor(Math.random()*100)%10==0){
                $("#"+name).fadeOut(250).promise().done(function(){
                    $("#"+name).remove();
                });
            } else {
                shunt(name);
            }
        }, memory);
    }

    function gribset(x,y){
        // From the x,y coordinates, grab the nearest
        // grid space and make sure there isn't something
        // in that space already. (We dont need to stack,
        // layers, just change the color of the last one)
        var index_X = Math.floor(x/size);
        var index_Y = Math.floor(y/size);
        var name = index_X + "_" + index_Y + "_cell";
        var exists = document.getElementById(name);
        if(exists == null){
            $("body").append("<div id='"+name+"'></div>");
            $("#"+name).css({'display': 'none'});
            $("#"+name).fadeIn(250).promise();
        }

        // Now add the color, place the tile,
        // and pretty it up with some css.
        var color = toCSS(rcv(), rcv(), rcv());
        $("#"+name).css({
            'position': 'absolute',
            'background-color': color,
            'box-shadow': '0 0 1px '+color,
            'border-radius': '2px',
            'top': index_Y * size,
            'left': index_X * size,
            'width': size-3,
            'height': size-3
        });
        return name;
    }

    // Pick a direction, and animate the
    // movement of the tile to the outside
    // of the page. Once that is done, remove it.
    function shunt(name){
        var d = goDirection();
        var direction = d[0];
        var magnitude = d[1];
        var animation = {};
        var time = Math.floor(Math.random() * 600 + 300);
        animation[direction] = magnitude;
        $("#"+name).animate(animation,time).promise().done(function(){
            $("#"+name).remove();
        });
    }

    // A demo function that places a tile at a random
    // location at a random time interval.
    function demo_gribble(){
        var x = Math.floor(Math.random()* $(document).width());
        var y = Math.floor(Math.random()* $(document).height());
        var time = Math.floor(Math.random() * 450 + 50);
        gribble(x,y);
        setTimeout(function(){
            demo_gribble();
        }, time);
    }

    $(document).ready(function(e){
        // Style up the body.
        $('body').css({
            'width': '100%',
            'height': '100%',
            'background-color': '#111',
            'overflow': 'hidden',
            'position': 'absolute'
        });

        // Let users click to add a gribble-tile.
        $(document).click(function(e){
            var x = e.clientX;
            var y = e.clientY;
            gribble(x, y);
        });

        // Run the demo function
        demo_gribble();
    });

A little bigger than last time, but still not bad at all.
[Here's the full fiddle](https://jsfiddle.net/28p6ox9b/4/) if you want to mess with it.
]]></content:encoded>
      <dc:date>2016-05-21T00:00:00-07:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Xen fsck'd My Grub!</title>
      <link>http://konstantinfarrell.github.io/2016/05/fsck</link>
      <description><![CDATA[

]]></description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 May 2016 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>http://konstantinfarrell.github.io/2016/05/fsck</guid>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[![Error Loading Operating System](/files/img/error_loading.png)

# One Does Not Simply Post Errors Without Context

So I was installing Xen on my CentOS VM.
Probably not the best idea to begin with, but it's a dependency for some
software that is made by a company I recently applied for a postion at.
Chances are, once they discover the absolute mess I made just trying to
get the dang dependencies working, they will have a much easier time
determining whether to hire me or not.

After the installation process, you have to reboot, and boot into Xen.
When I went to do this, I was met with the VirtualBox startup splash screen,
immediately followed by the grub bootloader screen, and a list
of operating systems to choose from. Xen was automatically selected so I let
it count down and begin booting.

However, instead of booting normally, I was once again met with the VirtualBox
startup screen, the bootloader, and the list of OS's.

## Shoulda' Backed It Up.

To remedy this situation, I thought I could just wait for the next grub screen to pop up,
select the old operating system, boot into that, uninstall Xen, and reboot to find my system
in roughly the same state as before the issue.

Oh just how wrong I was.

After booting into my old CentOS config, I went to `/etc/sysconfig/kernel` and set the param to `default`.
Then I punched in

    yum erase kernel-xen

And that's where everything went wrong.

When I went to reboot the VM, I was met with the command line of the grub bootloader.
And after a few minutes of poking around, I discovered that the contents of `/boot/grub/grub.conf`
had been erased entirely. Leaving nothing but an empty file in its place.

## How To Fix It

After hiding under my desk in the fetal position failed to produce any desirable results, I thought
to myself **"maybe the problem would be fixable if I actually tried to fix it."**

My first attempt involved trying to boot the VM from a live USB, and simply copying the `grub.conf`
file over. However this ultimately proved unsuccessful as the operating systems had different configurations.
(One was vanilla CentOS, the other was a Vagrant-provisioned CentOS install.)

Attempting to boot from the other grub file just caused the box to crash.

Next I tried unmounting the VM, mounting the disk as a filesystem on another VM, and extracting the critical files.
This worked well, and I was able to move all critical files from the old disk onto the new disk. From there
I was able to reinstall the VM, and restore it to its original working state by moving all the critical files I
needed back onto it.

The only thing left to do was to reinstall some of the programs that had gone missing.

## Conclusion

So maybe this post didn't go quite as advertised. I wasn't able to restore the original VM with all the original
files, but I was able to essentially copy it all into an identical machine. Hopefully next time I can be smart about
it and actually backup my VM before trying to do something like that.
]]></content:encoded>
      <dc:date>2016-05-19T00:00:00-07:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>System Font Size in Headless CentOS 7</title>
      <link>http://konstantinfarrell.github.io/2016/05/fonts</link>
      <description><![CDATA[

]]></description>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 May 2016 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>http://konstantinfarrell.github.io/2016/05/fonts</guid>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[![Terminal](/files/img/terminal.png)

It took a little bit of digging to find this one, so I'm posting it for future reference.

If you happen to be running CentOS 7 in headless mode on an AMD processor (can you say niche?)
and have wanted to change the system font family or size, look no further than `terminus-fonts-console`.
It's a pretty neat little utility that does it all for you.

First install it with `yum`, then set the system font to whatever you like. The supported font types
are listed on their package [site](https://pkgs.org/centos-6/centos-i386/terminus-fonts-console-4.30-1.el6.noarch.rpm.html).

In my case, I wanted a bigger font, so I used `ter-d22b`

    yum install terminus-fonts-console
    setfont ter-d22b.psf.gz
    echo setfont ter-d22b.psf.gz >> /etc/rc.local

This may not apply to you, but in my case it did as I was using a fresh install of CentOS.

Make sure you set the executable bit.

    chmod +x /etc/rc.d/rc.local

And just like that your new system font is ready to go.
]]></content:encoded>
      <dc:date>2016-05-15T00:00:00-07:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Backgrounds with Changing Colors</title>
      <link>http://konstantinfarrell.github.io/2016/05/gradiate</link>
      <description><![CDATA[

]]></description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 May 2016 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>http://konstantinfarrell.github.io/2016/05/gradiate</guid>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<iframe src='/static/lib/colors.html'></iframe>


Color changing backgrounds are a pretty cool effect to have on your site if done correctly.
And they also make for a neat little programming exercise for when you're bored.
Here I'm going to give a tutorial on how to implement a color changing
background in jQuery.

Feel free to follow along using this [fiddle](https://jsfiddle.net/cem8ukfr/8/) I have prepared.


# Step 1. Setup the page.

Lets just start out with a call to the ready function

    $(document).ready(function(){
        // Here's where everything happens
    });

If you are following along in jsFiddle, this is already supplied along with some css.

The first order of business is to think about how the background color is defined. The
easiest way to do this is with RGB values. So we're going to need 3 variables
to hold each value between 0 and 255.

I'm going to define a function to do that instead of typing out the code 3 times.
Since the rgb values will have to be put into string format before they can be used
for manipulating css, it would be convenient to do that in this function too.

So my code now looks like this.

    // Take RGB values and return a CSS formatted string representation.
    function toCSS(r,g,b){
        return "rgb("+r+","+g+","+b+")";
    }

    // Return a pseudorandom number between 0 and 255
    function rcv(){
        return Math.floor(Math.random()*256);
    }

    $(document).ready(function(){
        var r = rcv();  // variable for red
        var g = rcv();  // variable for green
        var b = rcv();  // variable for blue

    });

The next step is set the background color, and figure out a way to make it cycle.
So on the last line of the `$(document).ready();` call, right before the closing `});`
, add the following line.

    $('body').css('background-color', toCSS(r,g,b));

Now if you refresh the page, you should see the background color change to
something random each time.

# Step 2: Make the colors change

This part is a little more tricky. Making the colors change isn't very difficult because all we
really need to do is to add a function that slightly changes each color value, and then call that
function periodically (lets start with every 50ms) in order to achieve a smooth transition.

To do this we can add this right below the `$('body').css` call.

    var delay = 50;    // pause 50 milliseconds before changing the background.
    function transition(r, g, b){
        var color = toCSS(r,g,b);                   // get the background color.
        $('body').css('background-color', color);   // and apply it.

        setTimeout(function(){
            transition(r+1, b+1, c+1);      // now increment the colors and call
        }, delay);                          // the function with the function with
    }                                       // the new values.

The tricky part comes when we consider the fact that each color
value can only go from 0-255. So if our function incrementally changes
each color value, it has to be able to handle the restriction on the
input bounds.

The immediate solution I jumped to was using the modulo operator.
However, after a little consideration I came to realize that this would
enable smooth transitions, only up until a color value reached 255. Then
there would be a sharp change as that particular color jumped back down to 0.

# Step 3: Make the colors change...better.

To address this lets just look at some nice mathematical properties.

Namely the properties of `-1^n` when `n >= 0`. The function `f(n)= -1^n` will oscillate
infinitely between `1` and `-1`, which can be used as an indicator for which direction the
color value is changing. As long as we want to stay out of trouble, `n` should remain
an integer. So if we modify the function slightly to consider both the 0-255 range, and the
integer constraint, we get something like `f(n) = -1^(Math.floor(n/255))`.

As you can see, this function will remain positive for the first 255 values.
This models the initial incremental motion of the color values.
Once the input is greater than 255, the value shifts to -1,
indicating the change in direction as the colors begin to descend from 255 back to 0.

With this in mind, we can add a helper function that takes in any value (0-infinity),
and returns a value between 0 and 255 taking oscillation into consideration by first
determining whether the direction is positive or negative using the `-1^n` method, then either returning
that value mod 255, or returning the difference between the 255 and the former.

    function colorValue(n){
        var dir = Math.pow(-1, Math.floor(n/256));
        if(dir==1){
            return n%256;
        }
        return 255-(n%256);
    }

Now we can substitute the arguments in the `toCSS` function call with values returned by
this function.

    function colorValue(n){
        var dir = Math.pow(-1, Math.floor(n/256));
        if(dir==1){
            return n%256;
        }
        return 255-(n%256);
    }

    var delay = 50;    // pause 50 milliseconds before changing the background.
    function transition(r, g, b){
        var color = toCSS(colorValue(r), colorValue(g), colorValue(b));
        $('body').css('background-color', color);

        setTimeout(function(){
            transition(r+1, g+1, b+1);
        }, delay);
    }

# Step 4: Make it go.

Now we just add a call to the transition function from within our `$(document).ready();`
function, and pass in the `r`,`g`,`b` values that were defined previously.

    var r = rcv();
    var g = rcv();
    var b = rcv();
    $('body').css('background-color', toCSS(r,g,b));
    transition(r,g,b);

Voila. You should see it run.

## Here's the full script.

    // Take RGB values and return a CSS formatted string representation.
    function toCSS(r,g,b){
        return "rgb("+r+","+g+","+b+")";
    }

    // Return a pseudorandom number between 0 and 255
    function rcv(){
        return Math.floor(Math.random()*256);
    }

    function colorValue(n){
        var dir = Math.pow(-1, Math.floor(n/256));
        if(dir==1){
            return n%256;
        }
        return 255-(n%256);
    }

    var delay = 50;    // pause 50 milliseconds before changing the background.
    function transition(r, g, b){
        var color = toCSS(colorValue(r), colorValue(g), colorValue(b));
        $('body').css('background-color', color);

        setTimeout(function(){
            transition(r+1, g+1, b+1);
        }, delay);
    }

    $(document).ready(function(){
        var r = rcv();  // variable for red
        var g = rcv();  // variable for green
        var b = rcv();  // variable for blue
        $('body').css('background-color', toCSS(r,g,b));
        transition(r,g,b);
    });


Not too bad huh? All you gotta to do make it work is
add a script tag to the page you want it on, and point that at
this script.

Here's the [full fiddle](https://jsfiddle.net/53upk1c6/) if you'd like to see.
]]></content:encoded>
      <dc:date>2016-05-12T00:00:00-07:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Konstantin's Private Minecraft Server</title>
      <link>http://konstantinfarrell.github.io/2015/10/minecraft-server</link>
      <description><![CDATA[

]]></description>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Oct 2015 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>http://konstantinfarrell.github.io/2015/10/minecraft-server</guid>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[![Minecraft Screenshot](/files/server/img/screenshot.png)

# Lets Play Some Minecraft

This page has moved! Everything is now hosted on the server itself!
Go [check it out!](http://tardigrade.ddns.net)
]]></content:encoded>
      <dc:date>2015-10-13T00:00:00-07:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lets Learn Some Python</title>
      <link>http://konstantinfarrell.github.io/2015/07/python</link>
      <description><![CDATA[Before you begin

]]></description>
      <pubDate>Sat, 04 Jul 2015 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>http://konstantinfarrell.github.io/2015/07/python</guid>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[## Before you begin

You gotta know a few things about whats going on on this page. First, this guide is a quickstart so don't expect a detailed explanation of anything less than criticaly important.
Second, I write Python for web applications. So what I consider "the basics" may not be what you're looking for (though if you're a total beginner, you may get some use out of it).
Third, notice the date. 'murka. Aight, lets hop on our eagles and write some patriotic Python.

## Getting Started

You should have some sort of Python environment installed. You can use the terminal and a text editor like Vim to write and execute Python code, or you could use an IDE like Idle, or PyCharm.
I will focus primarily on running Python in a Linux based Terminal environment. If you're using Idle or some other IDE, you can skip to the next section.

Also I use Vim. Sorry Emacs users.

### Download & Install - Linux

Lets start by downloading, and installing the version of Python we are going to be using.

    wget https://www.python.org/ftp/python/3.3.6/Python-3.3.6.tar.xz
    tar xf Python-3.*
    cd Python-3.*
    ./configure
    make

If you're running a version of Red Hat, or use yum, use

    make altinstall

otherwise

    make install

Once that is all finished, you should have python ready to go.

### Download & Install - Windows & Mac

If you arent running a linux distribution, or just don't want to hastle with the command line then you can install Idle for free from Python's website. 

[www.python.org/downloads](http://www.python.org/downloads/)

Download and install Python 3.4.3, and open Idle once it's finished.

### Open a new Python file

For terminal users, cd to your working directory & open a new Python using

    vim new_file.py

or if you're using Idle,

    <ctrl> + n

### Run that code

If you're using the terminal, close your text editor and

    python new_file.py

or in Idle, simply press `F5`

## Some Handy Stuff to Know

### Comments 

    # either with a "#"
    """
        or as a block
        comment spanning
        multiple lines.
        You can use both
        single and double
        quotes for block
        comments
    """

### Input / Output

You can output to the terminal with `print()`

    print("Hello, world!")

Variable data types are implicit, so no type declaration is needed

    my_variable = "Set it to a string"
    another = 5
    yet_another = False

If you want to get user input, use the `input()` function and assign it to a variable.

    user_input = input("Say something!")
    print(str(user_input))

Make sure to always sanitize your input and output to avoid errors.

    output = my_variable + str(another)
    print(output) # => "Set it to a string5"

`str()` is a Python builtin that will output a string representation of the argument. It can be overridden in a class method.

### String Operations

There are also several handy string operations like

    len(output)                 # => 19 - the length of the string
    type(string)                # => string
    words = output.split(" ")   # => "Set", "it", "to", "a", "string5"
    output[0]                   # => "S"
    words[0]                    # => "Set"

### List Operations

    words.append("called")      # => "Set", "it", "to", "a", "string5", "called"
    words.pop()                 # => "Set", "it", "to", "a", "string5"


### Control Flow

Python comes equipped with all the bells and whistles you need to make your program run. Thanks to Python's focus on readability, control flow statements read exactly how they work.

if / else statements

    a = 3
    b = 5
    if a < b:
        print(str(a) + " is less than " + str(b))
    elif a > b:
        print(str(b) + " is less than " + str(a))
    else:
        print("They are equal")

for loops

    list = [1, 2, 3, 4, 5]
    for entry in list:      # note that the iterator variable
        print(str(entry))   # declaration statement is implicit

and while loops

    count = 0
    full = 20
    while count <= full:
        print(str(count))
        count++

### Functions

function declaration in Python is done in the following way

    def new_function(some_variable):
        """ This function is gonna do some stuff """
        result = some_variable.another_function()
        return result

since Python is interpreted, you need to declare functions before using them.

Function calls are done as expected.

    some_variable = "stuff"
    result = new_function(some_variable)

#### Classes

class declarations are done like

    class AwesomeNewClass(SomeParentClass):
        """
            The purpose of this class is to extend the
            functionality of SomeParentClass by being more
            awesome.
        """
        def __init__():
            """ this is the constructor """

        def some_awesome_function():
            """ does all the awesome stuff """

`NOTE:` You should fill in the functions with at least 1 line of code otherwise it will result in a syntax error

That should be enough to get you started. If you feel like I've missed something, please email me and I'll make changes as necessary. Again, this is a rough guide, and is not meant for people who have never programmed before. There are better, more comprehensive guides out there that would be a far better intro to programming for you.
Thanks for reading! More Python coming up soon!
]]></content:encoded>
      <dc:date>2015-07-04T00:00:00-07:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Getting Started with Ruby on CentOS 6.5</title>
      <link>http://konstantinfarrell.github.io/2015/07/post-getting-started-with-ruby-on-centos6.5</link>
      <description><![CDATA[Before you begin

]]></description>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jul 2015 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>http://konstantinfarrell.github.io/2015/07/post-getting-started-with-ruby-on-centos6.5</guid>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[## Before you begin

Hi guys. This is a quickstart guide to getting Ruby up and running on your CentOS 6.5 box. This guide is rough, and meant more as a reference for people who know/have worked with the language, but just need a quick refresher. It also works as a quickstart guide for ADHD kids like myself who don't want to do a lot of reading. Just keep in mind that there's gonna be a few things missing.

This guide assumes you have some level of proficiency in UNIX commands, and can infer what is happening in the code without many descriptive details. That beign said, if you think I missed something critical, feel free to email me and I will make adjustments as necessary.

## Lets begin now.

To install ruby on a CentOS 6.5 box, just type this into the terminal.

    yum install ruby
    yum install rubygems
    
Update everything

    gem install rubygems-update
    update_rubygems
    
Switch to a new directory and open a ruby file

    cd ~/new_directory
    vim test.rb
    
Put this guy at the top of your file

    #!/usr/bin/env ruby
    
Now you're set. Run your project with

    ruby test.rb
    
## Handy things to know

#### Comments.

    # comments are made with #'s
    =begin
    you can also do block level comments like this
    =end
    
#### Arithmetic, Logical and Comparison operators.

math is basically the same as python

    1 + 1  # => 2 
    1 - 1  # => 0
    2 * 2  # => 4
    2 ** 3 # => 8
    8 / 2  # => 4
    
same goes for equality and inequality

    1 == 1 # => true
    2 != 5 # => true
    
and comparisons

    1 < 3 # => true
    1 > 0 # => true
    1 <= 3 # => true
    1 >= 0 # => true
    
logical operators have high precedence

    true && false # => false
    true || false # => true
    !false # => true
    
and low precedence variations. These are meant more for control of program flow.

    true and true # => true
    false or true # => true
    
    nil # ruby's keyword for a null value.
   
#### Input & Output

I/O is quite simple in Ruby. To output values to the console

    puts "Hello, World!"
    print "You can also print with print"

And to get input

    name = gets # user inputs "Bob"
    puts name   #=> Bob

## More coming soon
]]></content:encoded>
      <dc:date>2015-07-03T00:00:00-07:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <dc:date>2016-07-16T00:00:00-07:00</dc:date>
  </channel>
</rss>